[Music]
hi I'm Jennifer from shabby Fabrics I
have a fun project for you today it's so
quick and so easy and so practical look
at this adorable bag made out of just
two fat quarters now I can think of a
thousand things to use this for when I'm
at the beach and I want to have my keys
and my phone immediately accessible and
not the bottom of my bag this is perfect
or maybe when I'm traveling to Quilt
Market or wherever I can put things that
I just you know makeup bag whatever so
lots and lots of uses for it now I
wanted to introduce you to these cute
bags that we have designed here at
shabby Fabrics is called the trendy
triangle tote that's hard to say that
fast trendy triangle tote um comes in
three colors purple we have aqua and
orange is so popular right now those are
available as kits now we made um our
bags coordinate uh with the larger bags
so when we go the beach like I said you
know your sunblock and your water isn't
potentially you know leaking and
damaging your cell phone or whatnot so
let's get started it is so simple and so
easy and it takes almost no fabric two
fat quarters um and even if you don't
have fat quarters if you have a quarter
yard even of two Fabrics that would be
more than enough fabric to do actually
probably two bags so let's look at this
here we have the main fabric which will
be on your your outside you'll need two
pieces that are 8 by1 your lining will
also be 8 by 10 we chose a heavyweight
fusible interfacing for the um just to
make it that's what gives it that
firmness so it's not all limp and it has
a little bit more body so it's just plus
it looks great it it travels better if
it's got that interfacing in it so just
a heavier weight interfacing you'll also
need a zipper a 14 in or longer zipper
and for the little tabs on the end you
want two 2x3 in tabs so let's get
started we went ahead in the beginning
and we cut out that interfacing that I
mentioned and we just ironed it to the
back of the main fabric we did that for
both pieces so let's go
ahead and grab a lining
piece and we'll grab our outer piece and
we'll grab our zipper now how you lay
this down of course is key so start with
your lining f fabric right side up
you'll start with your zipper now you've
got the right side of the zipper with
the actual pull and the wrong side we
want this right side up and you're going
to be running the zipper right along
that Top Line in fact if I line that up
with the lines on my ruler or on my mat
it just kind of helps me keep it all
straight so we're going to put that
zipper right along there and notice how
my zipper is definitely longer than my
pieces in and that's important cuz we'll
be cutting that off later and then the
top will be right side down and of
course you want to line this up one
right on top of
another and you'll just pin now when you
put your pin in you want to go right
through the top and you're going to rock
past where that zipper is of course and
you'll continue to
pin now we've done this with both a
zipper foot and a regular presser foot
and we were successful both ways so if
you have a zipper foot I do recommend
that but if you don't have a zipper foot
again we used a regular presser foot and
we didn't have any problems at all so
don't feel like you have to run out and
buy a new presser foot if you don't have
The Zipper I'll be using the zipper foot
today first thing we'll do once we get
this pin is we're going to take this to
the sewing machine and I'm going to sew
right along of course just along that
zipper and I like a little bit more of
the pink showing on my bag let me show
you that here
rather than sewing right exactly along
the zipper um kind of track we went a
little bit of a distance away why I like
doing that is a the zipper's cute I like
that pink showing through and it keeps
my fabric away from my zipper I don't
know if you've ever had a piece of
clothing where the fabric is like right
up next to the zipper and when you go to
unzip it jams if you keep a little bit
more of a distance away from the zipper
that helps eliminate the possibility of
that happening so we're we're going to
sew um a little bit of a distance away
rather than right bumped up exactly
against because I don't want to catch
that fabric in jam cuz I'm going to be
in and out of this bag a lot so we'll
take this over to the sewing machine and
let's just get that started and you're
going to have a bag put together in
absolutely no time and this is great for
gift giving too um what woman doesn't
like to have a few extra bags for a
variety of
reasons so with the zipper foot it just
seems like I think with most zipper feet
they're about they give you a little bit
more than a/ qu inch seam
allowance and that seemed to be rather
than us trying to bump up against the
zipper I just had my zipper foot ride
right along the edge of that um
interfacing
[Applause]
okay so let me show you now what this
looks like we'll put that aside for
now and I'm push that over there so when
you open this up you can see how this is
now in case and I'm seeing that pink and
that's what I was hoping for I wanted to
see the pink it keeps the fabric away
from the zipper to reduce the chance of
jamming
so what we'll do now is when you flip
this over you're going to want to line
up the lining with the outer portion
again and go ahead and take this now to
your pressing mat and we want to press
that there we go so that's just kind of
cuz you can see how the
fabric it wants to be here you have to
very deliberately kind of pull it away
and give it a good press so I'm going to
go ahead and continue pressing when I
come back we're going to go ahead and
put the fabric on the other side of the
zipper now that I have that turned and
pressed now let's sew the other half of
the bag to the zipper so just like
before we'll start with the lining right
side up make sure when you put the bag
over top of that the other the first
part of the bag that it's lined up
stacked one right on top of of itself
there and you don't see this fabric
sticking out left or right and that that
makes sense that it just needs to be
stacked one on top of the
other and then we'll put
the outer portion of the bag right side
together pin just like we previously did
with the zipper foot you'll sew along
turn and press when I come back I'll
take you to the next
step now that I have the second half of
the bag assembled to the zipper I'm
going to show you the next step now I've
done one ahead of time so it might be
easier to actually see them side by side
right along the the fabric that
parallels the zipper we did a top Stitch
now you'll definitely want to change
your presser foot at this time to a
standard presser foot that can also do a
zigzag so start off with a straight
Stitch and we just sewed right along the
zipper track and it just gives it such a
nice tailored look so that's kind of
more for style points than anything else
it doesn't really have a lot of function
other than I guess it does to a certain
degree and that it kind of just holds
everything there because the fabric
right now isn't really together you've
got this half and this half but they're
not a unit yet so it does kind of begin
to establish that kind of sandwich that
there's all of that is kind of tucked in
The Next Step however is not optional
now looking at if you if you've not used
zippers before you need to come
across the this portion of the zipper
and you can even do it over here as well
that you actually do a zigzag here so
that the zipper doesn't just go off the
bag you it needs to have an ending so
how we went about doing this is the
first thing I want to do is actually
open the zipper to a certain
amount that's because the bag will
actually be pulled through this opening
so this is an important step to do now
when you take this to the sewing machine
I found that the lining and the and the
outside tended to shift so I do
recommend going ahead and putting in
some pins just so that this doesn't get
a little catty Wampus with you when
you're sewing this down so you'd pin all
the way around you just keep
pinning I'm going to try to make this so
that you see it from the exact same
angle that I am so it's easier for you
to understand
this let's actually turn it this
direction okay notice the zipper is
moving to the right zipper's moving to
the right you can start here with a
zigzag coming all the way around
all the way around here all the way
around here go across the zipper region
so when you get to this portion what I
did was I just kind of held it Clos by
hand and I zip zigzag right across that
region all the way back and you can
cross this there's nothing wrong with
doing that it's not necessary this on
this side is necessary you must do that
but here is not necessarily uh important
to do that um the reason we did the
zigzag is the inside of the bag
I want to show it to
you you see that right there that seam
is in there if you do the zigzag it just
helps reduce fraying because you will be
in and out of that bag so that's that's
the only reason we actually did the
zigzag around this portion
so because we have the example here
let's just keep moving along so you
understand again just a recap decorative
Stitch yes that's kind of bonus points
zigzag especially across this portion
not an
option make sure you open your zipper a
good amount
zigzag here zigzag here kind of close
that opening keep going zigzag and stop
let's go to the next
step now that you've gone ahead and
you've secured that zipper closed and
this will be secured a little bit later
on we're going to go ahead and we're
going to trim that off now I don't want
to use my rotary cutter for that because
you know that's a good way to uh Nick
your blade in no time so I'm just going
to get in there with a regular pair of
scissors I don't recommend your favorite
sewing scissors again this going across
zippers and whatnot is doesn't do a
thing for the keeping your your you know
blades
sharp there we go so all right next
stage tabs these are the cute little
pull things on the other side on other
side of the zipper you'll take your tab
both of
them you'll fold the long side in a/ qu
of an inch and press and you'll repeat
that for the other
side and then you'll fold
that in
half and just like we did here I like
doing that e inch Stitch just inside
here and just inside here it just seems
to kind of hold it all together is it
absolutely necessary at least on the one
side yes yes cuz you want that closed
but on the other side no but still just
for symmetry I like doing that and
that's kind of a preference thing I've
done those ahead of time just to save us
a little bit of time now you'll fold
those in
half and you're going to go ahead and
you'll butt that right up against that
edge and I'm just
bracketing where that's
sitting there in between tail it's just
it's just kind of centered over the
zipper I'll do the same on this side I'm
going to take this to the sewing machine
I'm going to sew here and I'm going to
sew here when I come back we'll go the
next step now that the tabs are sewn on
you'll bring the right the outside of
the
bag together and we're just going to sew
a/ quar of an inch I'll just put in a
couple pins and let's do this together
it's a quick step and then we'll just
keep going the bag is very close getting
much closer to being done now so let's
go ahead and I'm just doing a standard
straight Stitch quarter of an inch if
you previously zigzagged make sure
you're not on the zigzag anymore I
forget that sometimes
[Applause]
now let's take that to that sewing or
the uh pressing mat and let's press that
open it's a pretty bulky seam so that's
why I like to press open anytime there's
a lot of bulk you should definitely
consider pressing seam open and in that
case you might want to shorten your
Stitch length just a little bit because
like with quilting seams get pressed to
one side or the other it's just kind of
a locking thing it works great
especially when one row is pressed to
one side in the next rows press the
other because then you get what's called
interlocking seams but whenever I do
press seams open I like to shorten that
Stitch length just a little more more
meet more stitches per inch so there's
just a little bit more Integrity um in
the bag especially if it's something
that'll be used a lot now that press is
seam that seam is pressed open now down
below I can
see my zipper what I'm trying to do
right now is I just want to I want you
to see so there's our zipper pull which
is centered over the zipper so I want to
Center that over basically that zipper
pull and we're going to go ahead and pin
that and we'll repeat the same for the
other side of
course you know when I first started off
crafting and and quilting I really was
not a Penner I just want I didn't want
to waste the time I did couldn't be
bothered and I just went for it well you
know what I ended up doing end up
spending a lot of time seam ripping just
get over it just pin it is so worth it
because seam ripping is a complete drag
nobody enjoys doing that same thing on
the side I want to Center this over top
of my zipper region now this is a lot of
bulk coming in here because you're going
over many layers plus that interfacing
plus your zipper so make sure um you
know you're just ready and sometimes
when it's a lot of fabric you almost
have to kind of hand crank it over those
areas because your machine can kind of
get bogged down um I recommend getting a
certain amount of speed going with your
machine I actually want to show you that
let's let's do this together so you know
what I'm talking about I know we've
we've seen when there's so much it gets
bogged down but let's throw this
together I'll come over here so you can
see this better and I'm going to keep a
fairly good Pace going so that it
hopefully doesn't get bogged down at
that Center portion but if it does I'll
just hand crank it so let's do this
[Music]
together there's that tough part but
notice how I kind of just kept going
that seems to kind of help it not get
bogged down now I'll repeat that for the
other side let's just do that together
so we can just keep things going here
you can see that
again oh see that one got a little bit
bogged down so I'm just going to baby it
through that area I don't want to break
my needle or my thread there we go good
I got to show you example of both so
when it kind of does does get bogged
down or what happened there was that
flap started to turn over it's like well
you have to stop so but that's crafting
and quilting that's just how it
works
okay so now and we're so close to having
this bag done I'm
excited okay now that our bag is like
this we will go
ahead and prepare the corners which
creates this nice little box
section
so what we'll do now with our Corners
actually I remember this now this is
important because let me show you why I
want to what's called box my Corners now
if you don't clip your Corners you see
how I can't really press that seam open
watch this though if I I I'll use my
rotary cutter for that if be careful you
don't cut through what you just
sewed I'm just I don't know e of an inch
even maybe even closer than that by
doing that now when I try to box my
corner do you see how the seam will lie
open so that's why that's an important
step and I'm even going to press that a
little bit just so that I can get a
better visual so what am I meaning by
box the corner well just like I did I
made a clip now I want you to see
this I'm going to go ahead I'm going try
to get this out way so you can see what
I'm
doing this is where one of those little
um Omni grip rulers is absolutely
essential just get one in your sewing
room if you don't have one get one you
need
it what you're looking for is actually
two
measurements I'm looking for an inch and
a half which is about right there in
this distance and then left to right I'm
looking for 3 in when you find that
intersection you are at the right
place about
like about like
that yes and you're going to go ahead
and you're going to draw a
line now you're going to do the same
step for all
Corners you can
either draw one
and try to do them all and then take it
to the sewing machine or one at a time
personally I think it's easier to do one
at a Time come back do the other Corner
draw the line so so I want to do this
with you we'll do the one side together
and then you do the other three on your
own so I put a pin there cuz I just
don't want it to move I'm going to do a
straight Stitch here on the sewing
machine and then I'll show you what we
do with that corner
[Music]
make sure when you come to that seam
allowance is pressed open and I'm just
using my fingers here to hold that open
so when my presser foot comes up it
doesn't move that flap over like it
wants
to now what I'll do is I'll come to my
mat and you can even
just uh cut a visual quarter or if
you're like I'm not comfortable with
that you can go ahead and put your ruler
here it's a little bit awkward because
there is a lot of bulk but if you want
something to cut you know push up
against by all means use the ruler so
that see how that creates that's what's
creating this corner you're going to
repeat that for this corner and this one
and this one when I come back then
literally all you have to do then is
turn the back right side
out so I've boxed all four corners I
wanted you to see what that would look
like prior to turning and then my
absolute favorite part probably your
favorite part too is just turning it
right side out and seeing what your
finished project looks like and I you
know what when I made the first one I
was like I cannot wait to make this
again for every person I know they're
going to be getting means for Christmas
this year so isn't this so cute so
practical and just turn it right side
out kind of with your fingers you can
kind of press out where those
little uh box Corners are zip it close
and you're ready to go I hope you
enjoyed this fun practical DIY video
from shabby Fabrics
[Music]